Elwood R. Quesada Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Elwood R. Quesada Papers 1927-1960
MSS37135
Quesada, Elwood R. (Elwood Richard), 1904-1993
2,450 items
7 containers
2.8 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Air force officer and public official. Correspondence, memoranda, speeches and statements, reports, drawings, press releases, and other material pertaining primarily to Quesada's career as a United States Air Force officer and as director of the Federal Aviation Administration.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Quesada, Elwood R. (Elwood Richard), 1904-1993.
Organizations
United States. Air Force. Board of Review for Tactical Operations.; United States. Air Force. IX Fighter Command.; United States. Air Force. IX Tactical Air Command.; United States. Federal Aviation Administration.; United States. Joint Chiefs of Staff. Joint Task Force-3.
Subjects
B-36 bomber.; Nuclear weapons--Testing.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Africa, North.; World War, 1939-1945--Europe.
Places
Eniwetok Proving Grounds (Marshall Islands); United States--Armed Forces.
Titles
Elwood Richard Quesada papers
Occupations
Air Force officers.; Public officials.
Provenance
The papers of Elwood R. Quesada, air force officer and public official, were given to the Library of Congress by Quesada in 1954 and 1960.
Other Repositories
Additional Quesada papers are at the Dwight D. Eisenhower Library and Museum in Abilene, Kansas.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Elwood R. Quesada are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1904, Apr. 13 Born, Washington, D.C.
1923 1924 Attended University of Maryland, College Park, Md.
1924 1925 Army Air Service
1927 Commissioned as an officer in the Army Air Corps
1927 1928 Engineering officer, Bolling Field, Washington, D.C.
1927 1928 Attended Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
1928 1930 Aide to Major General James Fechet
1930 1932 Assistant military attaché, Cuba
1932 Promoted to first lieutenant
1935 Promoted to captain
1937 1938 Flight commanding officer, 1st Bomb Squadron, Mitchel Field, N.Y.
1938 1940 Technical advisor to the Argentine air force
1940 1941 Assigned to intelligence in the Office of the Chief of the Air Corps
1941 1942 Commanding officer of the 33rd Pursuit Group, Mitchel Field, N.Y.
1942 Promoted to lieutenant colonel
1942 Promoted to brigadier general
1943 Commanding officer, 1st Air Defense Wing and 12th Fighter Command, North Africa
1943 Commanding general, IX Fighter Command, England
1944 Promoted to major general
1945 Returned to the United States as assistant chief of air staff for intelligence
1947 Promoted to lieutenant general
1949 1951 Commander of Joint Task Force-3
1951 Retired from the United States Air Force
1958 1961 Administrator, Federal Aviation Administration
1993, Feb. 9 Died, Washington, D.C.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Elwood Richard Quesada (1904-1993) span the years 1927-1960 and consist of correspondence, memoranda, reports, drawings, speeches, charts, Quesada’s personnel file, and other material.
The bulk of the collection consists of material compiled by units under the IX Fighter Command and IX Tactical Air Command at the end of World War II to reflect the contributions of each unit to the war effort. The correspondence includes letters written and received by Quesada during his deployment to North Africa and Europe, 1943-1945. Other correspondence relates to the unification of the armed forces, the B-36 investigation, and Quesada's deployment to the Pacific in 1951 as commander of Joint Task Force-3 during a series of atomic tests on the Pacific atoll of Eniwetok.
Included in the collection is Quesada's personnel "201" file; documents relating to operations and training during World War II; speeches and statements by Quesada, including speeches given while he was administrator of the Federal Aviation Administration; and items relating to the Untied States Air Force Board of Review for Tactical Operations.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material or topic.
Container List
- B-36 investigation, 1949 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1943-1951, (13 folders) (Box 1)
- Federal Aviation Administration, 1958-1959, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Operation "Q," 1944, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Personnel "201" file (Box 2)
  - 1927-1944, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - 1945-1951, (3 folders) (Box 3)
- Project Chore, 1949 (Box 3)
- Report on German defeat, 1945 (Box 3)
- School of Air Support, Royal Air Force, Old Sarum, England, 1945 (Box 3)
- "Site Selection Survey: Additional Airport for Washington, D.C.," 1957 (Box 3)
- Speeches and statements (Box 3)
  - By others, 1947, undated (Box 3)
  - By Quesada (Box 3)
    - 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - 1950-1960, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4)
- Statistical data regarding operations, 1945 (Box 4)
- Unification of the armed forces, 1945, undated (Box 4)
- Unit histories, IX Fighter Command and IX Tactical Air Command, 1945 (Box 4)
  - 48th Fighter Group (Box 4)
  - 64th Airdrome Squadron (Box 4)
  - 67th Tactical Reconnaissance Group, (1 folder) (Box 4, Box 5)
  - 365th Fighter Group (Box 5)
  - 474th Fighter Group, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - 554th Signal Aircraft Warning Battalion (Box 5)
  - A-1 (Box 5)
  - A-2 (Box 5)
  - A-3 (Box 5)
  - A-4 (Box 5)
  - Adjutant General (Box 5)
  - Chaplains Section (Box 5)
  - Chemical warfare (Box 5)
  - Communications (Box 5)
  - Control Section (Box 5)
  - Finance Section (Box 6)
  - G-2 (Box 6)
  - G-3 (Box 6)
  - General, 1943-1945, (15 folders) (Box 6)
  - Intelligence (Box 6)
  - Judge Advocate General Section (Box 6)
  - Medics (Box 6)
  - Operational Research Section (Box 6)
  - Ordnance (Box 6)
  - Provost Marshall (Box 6)
  - Public Relations (Box 6)
  - Quartermaster (Box 6)
  - Signal Section, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Special Services (Box 7)
  - Statistical Control Section (Box 7)
- United States Air Force Board of Review for Tactical Operations, 1949, (3 folders) (Box 7)